Finding aid for the Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Կարօ Մինասեան հայկական հավաքածու LSC.1632
UCLA Library Special Collections
Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Վերնագիր: Մինասեան հայկական հաւաքածոյ
1600-1968 Թուական: 1600-1968
UCLA Library Special Collections
Minasian, Caro
LSC.1632
34 linear feet (47 boxes, 1 half box, 9 oversize flat boxes, 2 map folders) Ծաւալ: 34 ոտք (47 տուփ, 1 փոքր տուփ, 9 մեծ տափակ տուփ, 2 քարտեզի պարան)
The Caro Minasian collection was acquired by the UCLA Charles E. Young University Research Library in 1968 from Isfahan born physician and collector, Dr. Caro Owen Minasian. The Collection consists of: Armenian manuscripts, among which is the noteworthy Armenian Gospel of Gladzor; Early Armenian printed books; Persian, Arabic, Ottoman Turkish and Urdu manuscripts which relate to Persian and Arabic lexicography, Persian literature and history, Shi'ite theology and jurisprudence, practical arts, philosophy, and logic; Persian calligraphy; artifacts and objects; and this collection which includes material relating to the Armenian community of Isfahan, Iran in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
Քալիֆորնիայի Լոս Անջելըս մասնաճիւղի համալսարանը 1968 թուականին ձեռք է բերել Կարօ Մինասեանի հաւաքածոն: Դոկ. Մինասեանը Պարսկաստանի Սպահան քաղաքում բժիշկ էր եւ միեւնոյն ժամանակ նա արխիվային նիւթեր էր հաւաքում: Այս հաւաքածոն բաղկացած է՝ հայկական ձեռագրերից, որոնց մէջ է Գլաձորի հռչակաւոր Աւետարանը, վաղ շրջանի հայկական տպագիր գրքեր՝ պարսկերէն, արաբերէն, օսմանեան թրքերէն եւ ուրդու ձեռագրեր: Այս ձեռագրերի նիւթերը հետեւեալ են՝ պարսկերէն եւ արաբերէն լեզուաբանութիւն, պարսկերէն գրականութիւն եւ պատմութիւն, Շիա աստուածաբանութիւն եւ օրենսդրութիւն, արուեստ, փիլիսոփայութիւն, տրամաբանութիւն: Հաւաքածոն կազմուած է պարսկերէն ձերագրերի նմուշներից, զանազան առարկաներից եւ պատմական իրերից: Հայկական այս հաւաքածոն՝ որը հիմնականում Սպահանի հայկական գաղութի կենցաղի մասին է, բաղկացած է նամակներից որոնք նաեւ առեւտրի մասին են: Հաւաքածոն ուշագրաւ է իր հաշուեգրերով, նկարներով, տպագիր եւ ձեռագիր գրքերով, նամակածրարներով, բացիկներով եւ փաստաթղթերով, որոնք 17-րդ դարից մինչեւ 20-րդ դարի կէսերի ժամանակաշրջաններից են:
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Մատչելիութեան սահմանափակումները
Թույլատրւում է օգտագործել հաւաքածոն հետազօտութիւններ անելու համար: Ի նկատի ունենալ որ, հաւաքածոն պահպանւում է գրադարանի շէնքից դուրս: Նախօրօք պայմանաւորուածութիւնը պարտադիր է հաւաքածոն դիտելու համար: Հաւաքածոն դիտելու համար խնդրւում է կապուել UCLA-ի գրադարանի հետ:
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. Please consult digital facsimiles instead of originals in Series 1: Correspondence.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Dr. Caro Owen Minasia, 1968.
Աղբիւր «ձեռք է բերում»
Հաւաքածոն ձեռք է բերուել Դոկ. Կարօ Մինասեանից, 1968 թուականին:
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942334253606533
Biography/History
The Caro Minasian Collection was acquired by the UCLA University Research Library in 1968. The late Professor Gustave von Grunebaum, director at the time of the Center for Near Eastern Studies, heard of the availability of Minasian Collection in 1966 and urged Narekatsi Chair of Armenian Studies, the late Dr. Avedis K. Sanjian, to contact Dr. Minasian and investigate the possibility of securing the collection. At a private meeting in London in 1967 between Dr. Avedis Sanjian and Dr. Minasian, Minasian was persuaded that the ideal repository for his collection would be the UCLA Research library. The majority of the funds for the collection were allocated by Chancellor Franklin D. Murphy, who was both convinced of the uniqueness of the collection and the importance of expanding the research resources of the university.
Կենսագրութիւն / Պատմութիւն
Կարօ Մինասեան Հաւաքածոն ձեռք է բերուել Քալիֆորնիայի Լոս Անջելըս մասնաճիւղի համալսարանի Գրադարանը 1968 թուականին: 1966-ին, Պրոֆ. Գուստաւ ֆոն Գրունեբաումը, այն ժամանակուայ Միջին Արեւելքի բաժնի կենտրոնի ղեկավարն էր: Նա լսել էր, որ Մինասեան Հաւաքածոն ծախու է եւ քաջալերել էր Նարեկացի հայկական բաժնի ղեկավարին, Դոկ. Աւետիս Ք. Սանճեանին, որպէսզի Դոկ. Մինասեանի հետ կապուէր եւ տեղեկանար եթէ հաւաքածոն կարելի է ձեռք բերուել: 1967 թւականին առանձին հանդիպման ժամանակ Լոնդոնում Դոկ. Սանճեանը, Դոկ. Մինասեանին համոզեց որ ամենից յարմար տեղը հաւաքածոյի համար UCLA-ի հետազօտական գրադարանն է: Դրամական Ֆոնդի մեծ մասը յատկացուել է Դոկ. Ֆրանքլին Մըրֆի կողմից, որը հաւատացած էր, որ այս հաւաքածոն չափազանց իւրայատուկ է եւ կարեւոր է համալսարանի հետազօտական աղբիւրները ընդարձակելու համար:
Scope and Content
The Minasian Collection of Armenian material, 1600-1968 consists of material pertaining to the life and history of the Armenian community of New Julfa, Isfahan in Iran and their relations with the British, as well as the people of India, Sri Lanka, Indonesia and other groups residing within the region of the Indian Ocean. The range and diversity of the material in this collection is noteworthy, and includes: a large number of correspondence; photographs; maps; periodicals; printed books; official legal documents; ecclesiastical documents; trade letters and documents; ledgers; and postcards. This material can be found in many languages which includes: Armenian, Persian, Arabic, English, Dutch, French, Russian, Urdu, several Indian dialects, Turkish, and Hebrew. This collection is a valuable resource for the study of the history of Iran and the city of Isfahan; the Armenian community of New Julfa, Isfahan; the history of India and Sri Lanka; as well as British presence within these parts of the world. This collection is also an important resource for the study of Indian Ocean trade and commerce in the 19th and early 20th centuries.
Minasian's original collection acquired in 1968 also comprised Armenian manuscripts, among which is the noteworthy Armenian Gospel of Gladzor; Early Armenian printed books; Persian, Arabic, Ottoman Turkish and Urdu manuscripts which relate to Persian and Arabic lexicography, Persian literature and history, Shi'ite theology and jurisprudence, practical arts, philosophy, and logic; Persian calligraphy; artifacts and objects. These materials have been separated out into other collections (see "Related Material" below).
Ընդարձակութիւն եւ Պարունակութիւն
Մինասեանի հայկական հաւաքածոն, 1600-1968, բաղկացած է Պարսկաստանում Իսպահան քաղաքի եւ Նոր Ջուղայի հայկական գաղութի կեանքի եւ պատմութեան վերաբերող առարկաներից, ներառեալ նրա Անգլիացիների հետ յարաբերութիւնները եւ նրա Շրի Լանկայի, Ինդոնեզիայի եւ Հնդկական Ովկիանոսի շրջանում ապրող այլ ժողովուրդների հետ յարաբերութիւնները: Այս հաւաքածոյի առարկաների տարատեսակները ուշագրաւ են: Հաւաքածոյում առկայ են մեծ քանակով նամակներ, նկարներ, քարտէզներ, օրաթերթեր, տպագրուած գրքեր, պաշտօնական փաստաթղթեր, կրօնական փաստաթղթեր, առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր, հաշուեմատեաններ, եւ բացիկներ: Նիւթերը բազամալեզու են՝ հայերէն, պարսկերէն, արաբերէն, անգլերէն, հոլլանդերէն, ֆրանսերէն, ռուսերէն, ուրդու, մի քանի հնդկական բարբառներ, թրքերէն, եւ եբրայերէն: Այս հաւաքածոն կարեւոր աղբիւր է Նոր Ջուղայի հայկական գաղութի կեանքը եւ սովորոյթները բացայայտելու համար. նաեւ Իրանի եւ Սպահան քաղաքի, Հնդկաստանի եւ Շրի Լանկայի եւ Անգլիայի այս շրջաններում ներկայութեան պատմութիւնը ուսումնասիրելու համար: Առաւել եւս, այս հաւաքածոն կարեւոր աղբիւր է Հնդկական Ովկիանոսի շրջանների 19- ու 20-րդ դարերի առեւտուրը եւ վաճառականութիւնը ուսումնասիրելու համար:
1968 թուականին երբ Մինասեանին հաւաքածոն ձեռք բերուած էր Քալիֆորնիայի Լոս Անջելըս մասնաճիւղի համալսարանի Գրադարանին կողմից, հաւաքածոն նաեւ բաղկացած էր՝ հայկական ձեռագրերից, որոնց մէջ է Գլաձորի հռչակաւոր Աւետարանը, վաղ շրջանի հայկական տպագիր գրքեր՝ պարսկերէն, արաբերէն, օսմանեան թրքերէն եւ ուրդու ձեռագրեր: Այս ձեռագրերի նիւթերը հետեւեալ են՝ պարսկերէն եւ արաբերէն լեզուաբանութիւն, պարսկերէն գրականութիւն եւ պատմութիւն, Շիա աստուածաբանութիւն եւ օրենսդրութիւն, արուեստ, փիլիսոփայութիւն, տրամաբանութիւն: Հաւաքածոն կազմուած է պարսկերէն ձերագրերի նմուշներից, զանազան առարկաներից եւ պատմական իրերից: Այս նիւթերը ուրիշ հաւաքածոներու մէջ զատուած են (տեսէ՛ք «Մինասեանի այլ հաւաքածոները» ներքեւը):
Organization and Arrangement
Collection is arranged in the following series:
1. Correspondence
1.1 Abcar Family
1.2 Tēr Hovakim Abrahamean
1.3 Arratoon Family
1.4 Galstanean Family
1.5 Tēr Hovsēp' Tēr Gevorgean Ēliaseants'
1.6 Mackertich J. Bamban
1.7 Eleazar Family
1.8 George Mackertich (Bamban)
1.9 Martyros Ter Joakim
1.10 Tēr Mesrovb Dawt'ean
1.11 Caro Owen Minasian
1.12 Miscellaneous
1.13 Mkrtumean (Mackertoon) Family
1.14 Sarkies Family
1.15 Zohrab Family
2. Bound Correspondence
2.1 Tēr Hovsēp' Tēr Gēorg Ēliazeants'
2.2 Petros Ênjrghalean
2.3 Manuk Gregorean
2.4 Martyros Ter Joakim
2.5 George Mackertich (Bamban)
2.6 Melk'um Marcar
2.7 Martiros Tēr Voskanean (Sarkies)
2.8 Armenian Church
3. Ledgers
3.1 M.A. Tēr Georgis
3.2 Jani Hovhanisian: Collected Ledgers
3.3 Hovnanian Brothers
3.4 Martyros Ter Joakim
3.5 Carapiet M. Johannes
3.6 Margar Karapet
3.7 George Mackertich (Bamban)
3.8 Miscellaneous
3.9 Business and Commerce documents
4. Diaries
4.1 Minas Aghanur
4.2 Martyros Ter Joakim
4.3 George Mackertich
4.4 Hovsēp' Mkrtich'ean
5. Persian letters and documents
5.1 Letters
5.2 Zill-us-Sultan
5.3 Mulla Ali Mirpanj
5.4 Fathali Shah
5.5 Historical notes and documents
5.6 Persian documents
6. Armenian Church Documents
6.1 Documents, Accounts, Lists
6.2 Kondaks
6.3 Paintings
7. Armenian Schools
7.1 Accounting
7.2 Armenian Philanthropic Academy, Calcutta
7.3 Board of Management, Armenian National Schools
7.4 Documents
7.5 Newspapers
8. Armenian Communities of Iran
8.1 Armenian folklore
8.2 Armenian historical documents
8.3 Armenians in India
8.4 Armenian villages in Iran
8.5 Charity
8.6 Documents from New Julfa
8.7 Electoral meeting
8.8 Armenian Genocide
8.9 History of New Julfa
8.10 Immigration to Soviet Armenia
8.11 Jews in Iran
8.12 Armenian last names in New Julfa
8.13 New Julfan Armenian Council By-Laws
8.14 Armenian converts in Persia
8.15 Photographs of Persian manuscripts
8.16 Mackertich J. Bamban
9. Announcements
10. Newspaper Clippings
10.1 Miscellaneous
10.2 Armenian Genocide
10.3 Persian
11. Journals and Periodicals
12. Postcards and Correspondence Envelopes
12.1 Correspondence Envelopes
12.2 Postcards
13. Photographs
13.1 Armenian communities in Iran
13.2 Los Angeles
13.3 Armenian villages in Iran and India
13.4 Caro Minasean
13.5 East Asia Armenian Community
13.6 Microfilms
13.7 Glass Plate Negatives
13.8 Portraits
13.9 Isfahan
13.10 Miscellaneous photographs
13.11 Persian history and social life
14. Mixed Items
14.1 Business
14.2 Calendars
14.3 Caro Minasian
14.4 Documents
14.5 Harut'iwn Tēr Hovhan
14.6 Hayastani Koch'nak
14.7 Literature
14.8 Manuscripts
14.9 Martin Sarkies
14.10 Medicine
14.11 Miscellaneous materials
14.12 Obituary
14.13 Paintings and Drawings
14.14 Post related material
14.15 Property deeds and transactions
15. Books
15.1 Martyros Ter Joakim
15.2 George Mackertich
15.3 Religious
15.4 History
15.5 Dictionaries
15.6 Medicine and Science
15.7 Mathematics
15.8 Literature
15.9 Social Life
16. Martin Sarkies Free Mason Materials
16.1 Free Mason garments, relics
16.2 Free Mason documents and books
17. Maps
17.1 Maps of Armenia
17.2 War Map
17.3 Other Maps
Կազմակերպութիւն եւ կարգադրութիւն
Նիւթերը կազմակերպուած են յետեւեալ կարգով՝
1. Նամակներ
1.1 Աբգար ընտանիք
1.2 Տէր Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան
1.3 Արաթուն ընտանիք
1.4 Գալստանեան ընտանիք
1.5 Տէր Յովսէփ Տէր Գեւորգեան Էլիազեանց
1.6 Մկրտիչ Յ. Բամբանեան
1.7 Եղիազարեան ընտանիք
1.8 Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան (Բամբանեան)
1.9 Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան
1.10 Տէր Մեսրովբ Դաւթեան
1.11 Կարօ Օուն Մինասեան
1.12 Զանազան
1.13 Մկրտումեան ընտանիք
1.14 Սարգիս ընտանիք
1.15 Զօրաբեան ընտանիք
2. Կազմուած նամակներ
2.1 Տէր Յովսէփ Տէր Գէորգ Էլիազեանց
2.2. Պետրոս Ընջրղալեան
2.3 Մանուկ Գրեգորեան
2.4 Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան
2.5 Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանի (Բամբանեան)
2.6 Մելքում Մարգար
2.7 Մարտիրոս Տէր Ոսկանեան (Սարգիսեան)
2.8 Հայկական
3. Հաշուագրեր
3.1 Մ.Ա. Տէր Գէորգեան
3.2 Ջանի Յովհանիսեան՝ հաւաքուած հաշուագրեր
3.3 Յովնանեան Եղբայրներ
3.4 Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան
3.5 Կարապետ Մ. Յովհաննիսեան
3.6 Մարգար Կարապետեան
3.7 Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան
3.8 Զանազան
3.9 Առեւտրական եւ վաճառականական փաստաթղթեր
4. Օրագրեր
4.1 Մինաս Աղանուր
4.2 Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան
4.3 Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան
4.4 Յովսէփ Մկրտիչեան
5. Պարսկերէն լեզուով նամակներ
5.1 Նամակներ
5.2 Զիլուս Սուլթան
5.3 Մուլլա Ալի Միրփանջ
5.4 Ֆատհալի Շահ
5.5 Պատմական ծանօթագրութիւններ
5.6 Պարսկերէն փաստաթղթեր
6. Հայկական եկեղեցուն վերբերող փաստաթղթեր
6.1 Փաստաթղթեր, Հաշուագրեր, Ցանկեր
6.2 Կոնդակներ
6.3 Նկարչութիւններ
7. Հայկական դպրոցներ
7.1 Հաշուապահութիւն
7.2 Հայոց Մարդասիրական Ճեմարան, Կալկաթա
7.3 Հոգաբարծութիւն կեդրոնական Գ. Քանանեան եւ Ս. Կատարինեան ազգային երկսեռ դպրոցներ
7.4 Փաստաթղթեր
7.5 Լրագիր
8. Հայկական գաղութները Պարսկաստանում
8.1 ժողովրդական մշակոյթ
8.2 Հայկական պատմական փաստաթղթեր
8.3 Հայեր Հնդկաստանում
8.4 Հայկական գիւղեր Պարսկաստանում
8.5 Բարեգործութիւն
8.6 Փաստաթղթեր Նոր Ջուղայից
8.7 Ընտրական հանդիպան զեկոյց
8.8 Մեծ Եղեռն (Ցեղասպանութիւնը)
8.9 Նոր Ջուղայի պատմութիւն
8.10 Ներգաղթ դէպի Խորհրդային Հայաստան
8.11 Պարսկաստանի հրեաներ
8.12 Հայկական ազգանունները Նոր Ջուղայում
8.13 Կանոնադրութիւն Նոր-Ջուղայի Հայոց Համայնական Խորհրդի
8.14 Հայ կրօնափոխերը Պարսկաստանում
8.15 Պարսկերէն մատեանների լուսանկարներ
8.16 Մկրտիչ Բամբան
9. Յայտարարութիւներ
10. Թերթերից հատուածներ
10.1 Զանազան
10.2 Մեծ Եղեռն (Ցեղասպանութիւնը)
10.3 Պարսկերէն
11. Շաբաթաթերթեր եւ ամսագրեր
12. Բացիկներ եւ ծրարներ
12.1 Ծրարներ
12.2 Բացիկներ
13. Լուսանկարներ
13.1 Պարսկաստանի հայկական գաղութներ
13.2 Լոս Անջելըս
13.3 Հայկական գիւղերը Պարսկաստանում եւ Հնդկաստանում
13.4 Կարօ Մինասեան
13.5 Արեւելեան Ասիայի հայկական գաղութը
13.6 Մանրաժապաւէն
13.7 Ապակեայ սալիկներ
13.8 դիմանկարներ
13.9 Սպահան
13.10 Զանազան լուսնկարներ
13.11 Պասկերէն պատմութիւն եւ առօրյա կեանք
14. Խառը առարկաներ
14.1 Առեւտուր
14.2 Օրացոյցներ
14.3 Կարօ Մինասեան
14.4 Փաստաթղթեր
14.5 Յարութիւն Տէր Յովհան
14.6 Հայաստանի Կոչնակ
14.7 Գրականութիւն
14.8 Մատեաններ
14.9 Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեան
14.10 Բժշկութիւն
14.11 Զանազան նիւթեր
14.12 Մահագոյժ
14.13 Նկարչութիւններ եւ գծագրութիւններ
14.14 Փոստին վերաբերեալ առարկաներ
14.15 Սեփականութեան փաստաթղթեր եւ գործառնութիւններ
15. Գրքեր
15.1 Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան
15.2 Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան
15.3 Կրօնական
15.4 Պատմութիւն
15.5 Բառարաններ
15.6 Բժշկութիւն եւ գիտութիւն
15.7 Թուաբանութիւն
15.8 Գրականութիւն
15.9 Ընկերային կեանք
16. Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանի մասոնական նիւթեր
16.1 Մասոանկան հագուստներ, մասունքներ
16.2 Ազատ մասոնական փաստաթղթեր եւ գրքեր
17. Քարտէզներ
17.1 Հայաստանի քարտեզներ
17.2 Պատերազմական քարտեզ
17.3 Այլ քարտէզներ
Related Material
The Minasian Collection of Armenian Material, ca. 1600-1968 (Collection 1632) makes up one portion of the Caro Minasian Collection at UCLA. The other components of the UCLA Caro Minasian Collection are as follows:
Minasian Collection of Armenian Manuscripts, ca. 1300-1899 (Collection 2089)
Minasian Collection of Early Armenian Printed Books (Collection 1612)
Minasian Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts, ca. 1100-1899 (Collection 1147)
[Minasian] Collection of Persian Calligraphic Samples, ca. 1100-1899 (Collection 1123)
Exhibit Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts (Collection 1656)
Photographic Album Collection, ca. 1860- (Collection 94)
Collection of Printed Books in Armenian, English, Persian, French (YRL Stacks, SRLF)
Artifacts and Items (UCLA Fowler Museum)
Separated Material
Material from collection 1632 has been moved as follows:
Armenian manuscripts have been moved to: Armenian Manuscripts, ca. 1300-1899 (Collection 2089)
Armenian scrolls have been moved to: Armenian Manuscripts, ca. 1300-1899 (Collection 2089)
Persian and Arabic manuscripts have been moved to: Minasian Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts, ca. 1100-1899 (Collection 1147)
Hebraic material have been moved to: Minasian Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts, ca. 1100-1899 (Collection 1147)
Leaves of Persian calligraphy have been moved to: Collection of Persian Calligraphic Samples, ca. 1100-1899 (Collection 1123)
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of Series 1: Correspondence are available electronically: Caro Minasian Collection of Armenian Material (306 items)
Iran-History-17th century--Sources.; Iran-History-18th century--Sources.; Iran-History-19th century--Sources.; Iran-History-20th century--Sources.; Julfa (Iṣfahān, Iran)-History-Sources.; Julfa (Iṣfahān, Iran)-Commerce-History-Sources.; Armenians-Iran-- Iṣfahān-History-Sources.; Armenians-India-History-Sources.; Armenians-Iran-Politics and government--Sources.; Armenians-Iran-Social life and customs--Sources.; Armenians-India-Social life and customs--Sources.; Armenians- Southeast Asia -Social life and customs--Sources.; Armenians-Iran-Societies, etc.-Sources.; Iṣfahān (Iran)-Pictorial works-Sources.; Photographs-Iran-19th century.; Photographs-Iran-20th century.; Postcards-Iran.; Iran-History-Qajar dynasty, 1794-1925-Pictorial works.; Iran-History-Pahlavi dynasty, 1925-1979-Sources.; Iran-Periodicals.; Iran-Newspapers.; Minasian, Caro
- Correspondence: Նամակներ, 1778-1962; Series 1.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal, business, and ecclesiastical correspondence, papers, and documents of a number of Iranian-Armenian families and individuals, collected over the years by Caro Minasian. There are also other materials such as a few photographs, poems, maps, and cloth satchels. Materials are primarily in Armenian, Persian, English, as well as Dutch and Russian.
  Այս կարգը պարունակում է պարսկահայ ընտանիքների եւ անհատների անձնական, առեւտրական, եւ եկեղեցական նամակներ, թղթեր, եւ փաստաթղթեր, Կարո Մինասեանի կողմից հաւաքուած տարիների ընթացքին: Նաեւ այլ նիւթեր կան, ներառեալ մի քանի լուսանկարներ, բանաստեղծութիւններ, քարտէզներ, եւ փոքր պայուսակներ: Նիւթերը գլխաւորաբար հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով են, նաեւ հոլանդերէնով ու ռուսերէնով:
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital reproductions of Series 1: Correspondence are available electronically at http://minasian.library.ucla.edu/index.jsp
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  PORTIONS OF SERIES 1 HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. Please consult digital facsimiles instead of originals.
  - Abcar Family: Աբգար ընտանիք, 1823-1894; Subseries 1.1.
    This subseries contains personal and business letters and documents of Abcar family members and Abcar & Company. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, and English.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Աբգար ընտանիքի անդամներուն եւ Աբգար եւ կօ.- ին անձնական եւ առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Letters from Eghiazar Set' Sami to Gregory Abcar: Նամակներ Եղիազար Սէթ Սամիից Գրիգոր Աբգարին, 1823-1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abcar & Company and Ter Martyros Ter Joakim: Աբգար եւ կօ (կօմպանի) եւ Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովհակիմեան, 1846-1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mkrtum Abgarean: Մկրտում Աբգարեան (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Business related documents in Persian: Պարսկերէն լեզուով առեւտրին վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Business related documents in Persian: Պարսկերէն լեզուով առեւտրին վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Business related documents in Persian: Պարսկերէն լեզուով առեւտրին վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tēr Hovakim Abrahamean: Տէր Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան, 1806-1849; Subseries 1.2.
    This subseries contains personal and ecclesiastically-related letters of Tēr Hovakim Abrahamean. Materials are in Armenian.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Տէր Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանի անձնական եւ եկեղեցւոյ վերաբերեալ նամակներ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Hovakim Abrahamean: Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան, 1841-1843 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Church materials, Letters, Wills
    - Hovakim Abrahamean: Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան, 1844-1852 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Letters, Accounting
    - Letters from Hovakim Abrahamean to his son Martyros Ter Joakim: Նամակներ Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանից իր տղուն Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին, 1829-1831 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters from Hovakim Abrahamean to his sons Martyros Ter Joakim and Galstan Abrahamean: Նամակներ Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանից իր տղաներին Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին, եւ Գալստան Աբրահամեանին, 1832-1836 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Hovakim Abrahamean to his son Martyros Ter Joakim: Նամակներ Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանից իր տղուն Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին, 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Hovakim Abrahamean to his son Martyros Ter Joakim: Նամակներ Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանից իր տղուն Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին, 1841-1847 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hovakim Abrahamean: Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան, 1806, 1828-1832 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Hovakim Abrahamean to Agha Hovanjan Agha Eliaz (Minasian): Նամակներ Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանից Աղա Յովանջան Էլիազին (Մինասեան), 1829-1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Also contains some letters sent to Hovakim Abrahamean from others. Նաեւ պարունակում է Յովակիմ Ապրահամեանին ղրկած նամակներ ուրիշներու կողմից:
    - Hovakim Abrahamean: Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան, 1830-1874 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters from Grigor Abegha to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Գրիգոր Աբեղայից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830-1831 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Hannayi Nahapetean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Յաննայի Նահապետեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1828-1834 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Letter from Mesrob Nahapetean to Hovakim Abrahamean Նամակ Մէսրոպ Նահապետեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters from Hovhannes Stepannosean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Յովհաննէս Ստեփաննոսեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1831-1832 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hovakim Abrahamean and Khachatur Galstanean: Յովակիմ Աբրահամեան եւ Խաչատուր Գալստանեան, 1829-1832 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Barsegh Hovakimean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Բարսեղ Յովակիմեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Ter Geworg Alek'sianeants' to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Տէր Գեւորգ Ալեքսիանեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letter from Ter Ghazar Grigorean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակ Տէր Ղազար Գրիգորեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Ter Galust Hovsep'ean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Գալըստ Յովսէփեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1828-1830 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Martyros Ter Joakim to his Father Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Մարտիոս Տէր Յովակիմեանից, իր հօրը Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830-1839 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letter from Ter Martiros Khach'atirean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակ Մարտիրոս Խաչատիրեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Step'annos A. Khach'ikean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Ստեփանոս Ա. Խաչիկեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Nerses Ter Mkrtch'ean to Hovakim Abrahamean: Նամակներ Ներսէս Տէր Մկրտչեանից, Յովակիմ Աբրահամեանին, 1830-1839 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Arratoon Family: Արաթուն ընտանիք, 1907-1926; Subseries 1.3.
    This subseries contains correspondence, biographical notes, a legal document, and a photograph pertaining to the Arratoon family. Materials are in English.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Արաթուն ընտանիքին վերաբերեալ նամակներ, կենսագրական ծանօթագրութի ւններ, մի օրինական փաստաթուղթ, եւ մի նկար: Նիւթերը անգլերէնով են:
    - Nicholas Gregory Arratoon / Avdall Arratoon Thaddeus: Նիկողայոս Գրիգորի Արաթուն / Աւդալ Արաթուն Թադէոս, 1907-1926 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Galstanean Family: Գալստանեան ընտանիք, 1829-1885; Subseries 1.4.
    This subseries contains personal, ecclesiastical and business letters and documents of Galstanean family members and their relations. Materials are in Armenian and English.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Գալստանեան ընտանիքի անդամներին եւ իրենց ազգականներին անձնական, եկեղեցական, եւ առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Letters from Galstan Ter Hovakimean to his brother Martyros Ter Joakim: Նամակներ Գալստան Տէր Յովակիմեանից, իր եղբօրը Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին, 1838-1846 (Box 2, Folder 15)